University of Connecticut, Connecticut Transportation Institute Records 2013.0009
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, Connecticut Transportation Institute Records
1974-1979
2013.0009
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.25 Linear feet
The collection contains documents pertaining to the establishment of the Connecticut Transportation Institute at the University of Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of copies of the papers read at the conference inaugurating the Connecticut Transportation Institute in 1974.
History
"The 1974 Connecticut Legislature, through Public Act 370, directed the University of Connecticut, with the cooperation of the Department of Transportation, to plan and develop a program for the establishment of a Connecticut Transportation Institute, to be operative for the fall semester of 1975. "
"In response to the legislative mandate, a nine member committee was appointed by Vice President Kenneth G. Wilson from among the engineering, science, business and humanities faculties; Dr. Peter McFadden, Dean of the School of Engineering, was named chairman. Upon recommendation of the Committee, President Glenn Ferguson appointed Dr. Jack E. Stephens of the Department of Civil Engineering as Acting Director. Under this arrangement, the Transportation Institute Advisory Committee acted both as a policymaking board and a working committee. The committee and Dr. Stephens, with a modest amount of consultive assistance, and with the cooperation and assistance of the Connecticut Department of Transportation, has undertaken to prepare a realistic plan for a transportation institute that will effectively eliminate an important deficiency in our capabilities in regard to transportation problem-solving."
[from "A Program for the Development of the Connecticut Transportation Institute" located in the records.]
Additional information about the Institute, its programs, faculty and goals is available on the CTI website.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Connecticut Transportation Institute.; Archives (institutions).; University of Connecticut.
- Series I: Transportation Advisory Committee records, 1974-1979
  - Correspondence, 1974 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Development Program, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Growth Strategies" Richard J. Bouchard, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "State Direction in Transportation" Joseph B. Burns, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Demonstration Projects which havbe been successful" Robert Casey, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Compartmentation as a tool to reduce traffic congestion and improve the environment" Curt M. Elmberg, 1974 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Role of the University" Glenn W. Ferguson, 1974 Septemeber (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Federal direction in Transportation" John E. Hirten, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Management of Transportation systems" G. E. Hutchinson, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Funding--Problems and Possibilities" Edmund J. Mickiewicz, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "New Technology vc. Conventional Equipment" George Pastor, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Interaction of Transportation and Urban Development" William S. Pollard, Jr., 1974 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Energy Considerations" Woodrow W. Rankin, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Marketing Approach to Mass Transit" James E. Reading, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Complexities of Transportation Issues" John G. Wofford, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Getting off the Ground: Some thoughts about mass transit policy making" Stephen Zwerlling, 1974 September 24-25 (Box 1, Folder 16)